[Music]
Stanford
University okay we want to move on to
closed strings but before I move on to
closed strings it's my Habit to do a
little bit of mathematics first or a
little bit of
reminder and the thing I want to remind
you of
tonight is
technical it has to
do with the canonical formalism of
classical mechanics this is a
reminder and what I'm reminding you
about is nur's
theorem anybody remember nur's
theorem ner theorem is the theorem which
tells you about conserved
quantities and their connection with
um uh with
symmetries the connection with
symmetries is that for every symmetry
there's a conserved
quantity and in quantum mechanics the
conserved quantity becomes what I would
call the generator of the Symmetry we'll
come through but I want to remind you of
that before we uh before we jump into uh
some questions about String Theory just
so that we'll have it have it on the
Blackboard okay supposing we have a lran
let's see how much you
remember we have a lran and it depends
on a bunch of of coordinates and I'll
call the coordinates
cues what is the Lan dependon the lran
depends on the
q's and what
else the Q dots the time
derivatives now what's the canonical
momentum conjugate to a given Q what
there there may be many Q's all right so
what's the momentum let's call it P sub
I
that's the canonical momentum related to
the cuth
coordinate partial of L with respect to
the
velocity now I'm now I'm not going to
derive for you n's theorem I'm just
going to State it for you remind you
what it is suppose you have some
symmetry or it doesn't even have to be a
symmetry well yes suppose you have some
symmetry which involves a transformation
on the
qes it's a infinitesimal symmetry where
you just shift things by a little bit so
we'll write it by saying the shift in Q
under a particular symmetry operation
we'll just call
it variation of Q sub I we'll just call
it
uh um I don't want to introduce another
symbol let's just call it Delta Q sub I
it might be some function it might be
the I function of
Q times some small parameter
Epsilon when you make a small
transformation each Q changes by an
amount that might depend on all the
other Q's times a small Epsilon what's
an example well an example is rotation
in space the coordinates X and Y of the
position of a part particle if you
rotate a little bit the coordinates each
coordinate changes and it changes by an
amount proportional to the small angle
Epsilon would be a small angle here and
in that case you would have Delta X is
equal to Y Delta y * Epsilon Delta Y is
equal to minus X so you would have an
example of
this the conserved quantity which in
that particular case would be angular
momentum is constructed out of the PS
and the variations of Q's so I'm just
going to write down the formula for you
it's called the nther
charge it's also called in quantum
mechanics the generator of the
transformation often labeled capital
Q let's call it Nera just to remind you
n o e
nther anybody remember what it is it's
first of all a sum it's a sum over all
the coordinates they all
transform
nobody right I didn't think you
did it's the I
momentum times the shift in the I
coordinate maybe we should do it ah
let's not do an example this is the
formula I want on the Blackboard this is
the
transformation okay
oh this is the symbol that represents
the nther generator of the trans of the
uh of the
operation in quantum mechanics it
becomes the operator which creates the
small change the operator action on a
wave function which induces the Symmetry
all right so that's that's n's
theorem that quantity is
conserved and uh it's going to come up
why does it come up there all sorts of
symmetries in string theory but in
particular one particular
symmetry let's
now forget the mathematics of n's
theorem and come to closed strings
closed strings are strings without
ends here's a closed
string let's think of the Blackboard as
the XY AIS is X and Y
and there's the string projected onto
the XY uh plane now the string is
parameterized by a parameter for open
strings we call that parameter
Sigma and sigma went from what to
what0 to Pi how about closed strings
what should I run it to for closed
strings I'd be an idiot not to my run it
from zero to two PI right right so some
point on the string we will label
Sigma equals z which point on the string
it really doesn't matter but we pick a
point on the string once and for all and
we label it Sigma
0o if we had a little pen and we could
Mark the string we would mark it at
Sigma equals 0 over there then a halfway
around would be Sigma equal
Pi a quarter of the way around would be
Sigma = Pi / 2 and 3/4 of the way around
would be Sigma equal 3 Pi /
2 and we're imagining that there's a
directionality along the string the
directionality of increasing
Sigma there's a there's a a sense of a
kind of Arrow along the string which
tells us which direction Sigma is
increasing and it's this
way running out of ink
again
now a string is like a rubber band and
think of it as a kind of marked rubber
band we're going to remove those marks
before we're finished a marked rubber
band Sigma equals 0 Sigma equals 1° 2°
3° 4° all the ways around to
360° and that gives us a sense along the
string but now that sense along the
string the orientation of the string has
nothing to do with the clockwise or
anticlock wiseness in the XY
plane I drew it so that Sigma was
increasing in the clockwise Direction
but now I take this string I lift it out
of the Blackboard turn it around and put
it back on the
Blackboard uh that's a physical thing I
could do with a piece of rubber with a
rubber band I put it
back and there it is now Sigma equal 0
was over here I happen to put it back in
the same place Sigma = Pi / 2 here Sigma
= Pi over here Sigma = 3 Pi / 2 over
here Sigma increases in this direction
now the only point I is I don't want you
to get confused when I speak of
orientation of the string it's not an
orientation in space it's a sense of a
sense of intrinsic to to the string
there's a directionality along
it and that directionality we have to
keep track
of okay now let's come to waves moving
along the
string a
wave can move either to the right or to
the left but by right and left I now
mean in the direction of increasing
Sigma or decreasing Sigma I do not I am
not implying anything about the spatial
orientation I am just imagining a little
wiggle in the
string and a little wi wiggle in the
string
proceeds in direction of increasing
Sigma I will call that a Right Moving
wave now if I turn the string
over and planted it back on the
Blackboard a Right Moving wave would be
moving in the opposite direction so it's
not the question of whether it's moving
moving clockwise or anticlockwise in
real space it's whether it's proceeding
from smaller Sigma to larger
Sigma
yeah yeah you can think of yes in
particular in the original in the
origins of string theory if you break
the string the only way to break a
string is to produce a quark and an
antiquark it's the question of which end
is the quark and which end is the
antiquark right now that doesn't mean
that you can't invent string
theories where the string is not
oriented but then you can't break them
but um let's for the moment pretend that
the string is oriented has a sense of
increase and a sense of
decrease all right what can we say first
of all what are the coordinates
describing the string
the coordinates are exactly the same as
they were for the open string an X of
Sigma and a y of
Sigma and if we have more coordinates
like kuta and Klein told us to do we
would add them in X of Sigma and Y of
Sigma the XY position the X and Y
position of the point Sigma
okay let's draw the sigma axis here's
the sigma axis it goes from 0 to 2 pi
I now remember when we were doing open
strings we had to worry about boundary
conditions what goes on on the ends of
the string here there are no ends of the
string but there is something that you
can call a boundary Condition it's the
boundary condition of the
relationship between the coordinates at
0 and 2 pi what's it going to
be X of zero must what equal X of 2 pi
because it's the same point you go all
the way around so that means if I were
to plot X's of Sigma they could be any
functions as long as they well this
overhang here is no good but as long as
it comes back to the same value after it
goes around by 2
pi
so X of 2 pi is equal to X of 0 same
thing with y
y y of 2 pi is equal to Y of
0 those are the two degrees of freedom
and now we can now we can imagine waves
let's uh let's start with the string
being let's start with a string just
being flat and having a little wiggle in
it it has a little wiggle the wiggle can
move to the left or it can move to the
right if it moves to the right that's
the that's the sense of increasing Sigma
it moves to the right that's a Right
Moving wave what happens when it gets to
the end of the
string it just reappears at the other
end so it might fall off the end over
here and uh you pick it up over
here and it just would continue to
circulate around and around the
string that would be the um the picture
of a Right Moving wave so that's a wave
moving to the right and then there are
waves that can move to the
left left moving waves and Right Moving
waves and both of them can exist on the
string what about for the open string
were there left moving waves and Right
Moving waves yeah you could imagine a
left moving wave and a Right Moving wave
you start with a left moving wave but
what happens when it gets to the end in
that
case it gets reflected so in that case
you would have left going to right going
to left going to right the leftin and
the ress of it would not be conserved in
time uh the kind of things which are
conserved in time are the standing
waves but for a uh for a Clos string
there are running waves go to the left
and go they go to the right okay let's
talk
about writing
the oh well yeah let's uh let's
take particular kinds of waves now
particular kinds of waves would
correspond to plain waves moving up and
down the string let's say right moving
or left
moving now it's convenient to describe
the waves not by signs and cosiness but
by
exponentials let's erase this over
here exponentials are just linear x e to
the I Sigma e to the i n Sigma uh
exponentials are just linear
combinations of ss and
cosin in the case of the open string you
are either restricted to SS or cosiness
depending on whether it was dlay or
nimon boundary conditions for the Clos
strings you can have both signs and
cosiness but you can also have linear
combinations of ss and cosiness so you
can have exponential waves propagating
to the left or the
right and so the kind of waves that you
can imagine are e to the i n Sigma which
would be of course cosine Sigma plus I
in I
uh cosine n Sigma plus
I uh sin n
Sigma we can choose to decompose things
into
exponentials in this way if we
like so let's do
that let's take X of
Sigma what we're going to do is exactly
what we did with the open string we're
going to we're going to Foria transform
X of Sigma but now the rule is neither
nman or disl just that it comes back to
itself after going around by 2 pi the
general form for the expansion of a
function which is periodic with a period
to Pi is just is a general form is that
it's a
sum of all
integers of coefficients let's call them
xn time e to the i
n
Sigma n can be positive or negative if n
is positive think of it as a Right
Moving wave if n is negative think of it
as a left moving
wave okay let's uh let's just check this
does this really have the property that
it comes back to itself when Sigma goes
from 0 to 2 pi when Sigma is zero e to
the i in Sigma is one what about when
Sigma is 2
pi e to the 2 pi is what e to the I * 2
pi is what
one how about e to tce 2 pi I one okay
right so every one of these supposing I
were to put over here instead of N I
would to put n/ two a
half does it come back to itself after a
a
cycle no so it's necessary to put
integers here and this is the most
general form of a periodic function when
it's for expanded on a line between 0
and 2 pi assuming that it's
periodic we're going to write this as
I'm going to write it as a sum of two
terms well a sum of three terms the
first terms are n for positive
n all right this is going to be a sum of
N greater than zero those correspond to
the Right Moving waves waves which go
around to the right now I want to write
the left moving waves which I could
write the same way except let N be
negative or I could write it as a sum of
N greater than Z but uh let's call it x
x- n e to Theus i n Sigma e to the I
sigas with positive coefficients here
correspond to Right Moving waves with a
negative coefficient that corresponds to
left moving waves
that's beautiful thank
you by moving don't you have to have
time coordinate yes see a sigma Sig
right yes yes the time coordinate is
usually in here e to the plus i e to the
minus I all right so think of these in
any cases left moving waves and Right
Moving waves something's missing
here n equals z right all right so let's
put that back
in and what is that any you know what
that is
hm it X zero but what's the physics of
it what's the physical meaning of
it Center center of gravity Center of
center of Mass center of mass of the uh
of the string the actual location of the
string uh the center of the string
x0 same thing for y exactly the same
thing for y I think I will not write it
but y of Sigma is equal to the same kind
of sum y subn e to the i in Sigma y ofus
n e to Theus I in Sigma so you can have
X you can have waves which correspond to
um uh fluctuations along the x- axis
waves which correspond to fluctuations
along the Y AIS they go around the
string and this is the general
form what do you do with this you take
the lran for the string which I haven't
written down but exactly the same L
grangian as for the open
string exactly the same the string is
still imagined to be made up of little
Mass points with strings and balls you
write the lran of the string exactly as
before the only difference is you
integrate now from zero to 2
pi the sigma
same thing as before DX by D to^ 2 to
time minus DX by D Sigma
s it's exactly what we wrote earlier and
we do the same thing for y plus
plus y
terms of exactly the same
kind so we have now a decomposition of x
into discrete Foria modes we have a
lran what are the time dependent things
in X of Sigma they're the
xns the xns are sort of coordinates
describing each oscillation each
oscillation has a shape but it also has
a Time dependence and the time
dependence is buried in the time
dependence of these X NS they are the
degrees of freedom
what do we do with this we take this
expansion and plug it into
here you can get x dot by
differentiating it gives you X do ins
and you can differentiate d x by the
sigma by differentiating these
coefficient functions
here we could plug into here and
calculate the
lran
uh for the whole
system lran I'm not going to do it
calculate the lran and what do we notice
about the lran what what what are the
xns going to be they're going to be
harmonic oscillators exactly as they
were before okay there will be harmonic
oscillators exactly as they were before
Oh before I do
that yeah before I do that let me uh do
something else first I don't want to I
don't want to write down the harmonic
oscillators I want to look at this
formula for a minute what is the energy
this is the lanan what's the energy
anybody
know same thing with a plus sign this is
potential energy this is kinetic
energy okay the X by D
to^ squar plus DX by D Sigma
squ likewise for
y I'm going to write this in a funny way
I'm going to write this as DX by D
to plus DX by D
Sigma
squared plus DX by D
to minus DX by D
Sigma
squared um I think I'm off by a factor
of
two it's probably a
12 can you see what's happening d x by
the squ here here the X by the^ squ we
double it that's why I put a 1/2 there's
also a DX by D Sigma squar and a DX by D
Sigma squ from here and then there's a
cross term the X by D to * d x by D
Sigma comes in with a plus sign here and
with a minus sign here and they cancel
this is the same as this do you have any
idea what the significance of this
decomposition
is okay a wave that's moving to the
right is a function of of Sigma plus to
a wave that's moving to the left is a I
may have it I may have opposite but the
a wave which is moving this way is a
function of Sigma plus to a wave moving
in the other direction is a wave moving
in the opposite direction
this is just the energy
stored I think this is left moving waves
and this is the energy stored in Right
Moving waves the Right Moving waves and
the left moving waves are transparent to
each other they just go right through
each other these are linear
equations linear equations of motion and
this is just writing the energy as the
sum of left moving waves and Right
Moving waves on the
string this will turn out to be of some
interest to us in a little
while now let's come to harmonic
oscillators each of these X's is itself
a harmonic
oscillator all right so we can now
start we don't need to go through the
details of constructing the harmonic
oscillators out of these things we can
pretty much guess there's going to be a
harmonic oscillator variable for each
mode of oscillation as always every time
there's a mode of oscillation you can
excite it excite it with creation and
Annihilation operators the creation and
Annihilation oh incidentally what is the
frequency of a
wave that's labeled by n
here it be the same as it was for the
open string proportional to n
the higher ends the shorter the
wavelength modes the higher the
frequency so that will be the
same okay so we have a collection of
harmonic oscillators but now we have
twice as many and the reason we have
twice as many is because we have waves
each
integer or each
frequency now labels two oscillations
one with that frequency moving to the
left and one one with that frequency
moving to the
right okay one of them is labeled with n
and the other one is labeled with minus
in there's too much there's much too
much notation but I can't help it there
are all these things that we have to
keep track of little n
here represents frequency when n is
positive as in the first term it
represents let's say waves going in One
Direction when it's negative it
represents waves going in the other
direction so let's now write down what
the various harmonic oscillators are we
first of all have create I'm not going
to bother writing the annihilation
operators the annihilation operators are
just the the conjugate the creation
operators can
create a
excitation moving let's say to the right
and then we'll just call it A+
subn it can also create a different
operator A+ of minus n if this one
creates a Right Moving wave on the
string then the other one creates a left
moving wave on the string okay so we
first of all have that
decomposition what
else well we have X and
Y I didn't write everything involving y
but writing y just replicates the same
thing for X what did I call a creation
annihilation operat is for the Y
oscillators last time I think I called
them B right so now we have more we have
B+ n and B minus sorry B+ n and B+ of
minus
n now I could add to this if I wanted to
write the annihilation operators four
more with minus signs up here I'm not
going to let us get confused by too many
pluses and minus signs A and B represent
X and
Y plus that's just creation operator it
excites the uh you can keep in mind that
there's also minus but we won't be using
it anyway and n and minus n have to do
well first of all n has to do with
frequency the frequency is just n but
plus n and minus n have to do with waves
moving in this direction or in that
direction that's the structure of closed
String Theory that's it that's that's
the whole structure of it but now we can
start asking what is the Spectrum what
kind of particles what kind of excited
States will a string have what's the
analog of the photon that we discovered
in the um in the open string you know
what I'll do I'll just remind you about
that for the open string we didn't have
this doubling of minus n and plus
n what we had was just creation
operators A and B
A+ n and B+
n we started I'll just remind you we
started with the ground state of the
string that's a string in its lowest
state of oscillation doing nothing then
you excite it what can you excite it
with you can excite it to get the lowest
energy you want to excite it with the
smallest n why because the frequency is
proportional to n and of course
frequency and energy are the same
thing so to get the lowest and next
lowest energy you want to excite it with
a plus of one and B plus of
one a + 1 and B+
one this is an an oscillation somehow
that's associated let's let's draw a
picture here's the
z-axis here's the x-axis and here's the
y-
AIS the string is going down the z-axis
with a huge momentum but it's
oscillating in the X the x- axis and in
the Y AIS do you remember what these two
things correspond
to they were photons these correspond to
the polarizations of the photons this is
an x-polarized Photon oscillating this
way no oscillating this way this is a y
polarized Photon oscillating in the
perpendicular Direction Direction how
about circular
polarization forward and
backward a + 1+ I plus orus I B+
one on
o i just being the complex number the
superposition of two polarization plain
polarized uh waves without the I would
just correspond to plain polarization in
some angle with the I it corresponds to
um to Circular
polarization okay so we'll just keep
that in
mind uh a plus I B and A minus IB create
uh units of angular momentum plus
angular momentum and minus angular
momentum okay so where are we
now let's see what we can make
the first thing we can presumably have
is the ground state and whatever the
ground state is it has some Mass squared
which I'll just call M
squared the ground state has some energy
M squar what excitations can I make well
I can excite it with
A+ uh one we have to to make the lowest
exitation we only want to use one here
we want to use one here we want to use
one here and we want to use one
here we don't want to excite it with two
units of energy so we don't want to use
A2 and
B2 okay what can we make it looks like
we can make four distinct
States four distinct
States uh which look like sort
of having two Photon or yeah looks like
they having two
photons um we could write a plus I and a
minus I or a minus one and B minus one
there's four possibilities now for
acting on the ground
state a + 1 or minus one or B+ 1 minus
one four distinct states that you can
make what could they correspond to what
kind of structure that they
have um
first question is how much angular
momentum do they
have how much angular momentum do they
have are they really like
uh oh let's see these are um
yeah this is basically the first thing
you can
make they're
not what's that they don't have to have
one no they do do have they do have one
unit of angular momentum they do have
one unit of angular momentum because you
could write them as a plus I and a minus
I one and minus
one so in essence it's just a doubling
of what we found here which means that
there are two kinds of objects both
looking like
photons right that doesn't sound so bad
but I'm going to tell you now right now
that this is not the right picture okay
not the right picture but to see that
it's not the right picture the thing to
do is to go to the next
level um number one if it were the right
picture then you would have two photons
each behaving like a photon there's no
angular momentum zero State here
incidentally there's no angular momentum
zero about that axis there's just A's
and B's A Plus IB a minus IB you can't
make angular momentum zero out of this
combination
that means something about these
hypothetical photons it means they're
massless if you had a massive Photon
then it would be able it would
necessarily be able to have angular
momentum plus about the axis of motion
angular momentum minus about that axis
and also angular momentum zero we
discussed that last time there's no
candidate for that here no candidate for
the angular momentum zero it's just like
having two angular momentum one and
minus ones
and that doesn't correspond to any
possibility other than massless
particles so we might say this Theory so
far has produced for us a doubling of
the photon
Spectrum okay but to see that that's
wrong you go to the next level let's go
to the next level what can you make
uh
um one unit up of
energy I'm getting a little bit tired so
I'm going to tell you what you get when
you make is a bunch of garbage it
doesn't look like anything sensible it
doesn't fall into rotational
multiplets it has um the wrong number of
states to be an angular momentum two and
there's no angular momentum one piece
it's just it's just a wrong uh it's just
wrong combination of
things this is not right this is not
right I'm going to tell you now why it's
right it's not right it's extremely
subtle and it's not easy it's not easy
well it's very easy but it's
[Music]
um a little bit
complicated not all the things that you
can write down correspond to legitimate
states of the
string in fact there are constraints
There are rules the rules forbid certain
combinations and I'm going to tell you
well you know what I'm going to do I
think I will not explain why tonight I
will explain why next time unless we
have some extra time tonight but um I'm
going to tell you what the rule is I'm
going to tell you a rule and then we'll
try to figure out why it's the
rule the rule is called level
matching and level matching says that
the Right Moving energy and the left
moving energy must be the same now you
ask me why why does the total amount of
energy going around to the right have to
be the same as the total amount of
energy going to the left that's a for
that we'll have to come back to nther
theorem okay but let's not do that now
let's just make it as a postulate let's
make it as an assumption that the Right
Moving energy and the left moving energy
must be
equal right what can we say about these
states well let's write let's see what
ones there are
this a
+1
o that has one unit of Right Moving
energy so doesn't satisfy the level
matching rule how about minus one has
one more unit of left moving energy
doesn't satisfy the level matching same
thing with
B either it has one unit of Right Moving
energy or one unit of left moving energy
so none of these states here that we
wrote down satisfy the condition that
the left moving energy and the Right
Moving energy are the
same not good States let's go to the
next level let's see what's at the next
level at the next level we can do the
following things we can
take a let's see what we
have we have um
a +
1 time a +
minus1 this has one unit of left move or
one unit of Right Moving energy and one
unit of left moving
energy
o that satisfies the level matching
condition because it has one unit of
Right Moving and one unit of left
moving I appreciate this is coming out
of nowhere why I'm requiring this to be
true but let's we'll come back to it all
right so this is a good State this is
okay what about
A+ and how much energy does it
have two units all right next we have A+
uh oh sorry next we have B+ of one B+ of
minus1 same thing perfectly good state
levels are matched as much left moving
energy as Right Moving energy and we can
have a + 1 B+ minus yeah B+ minus one a
positive unit um a Right Moving bit of
energy and a left moving bit of energy
this is also a good
State and what about uh A +
minus1 B + 1 o also good as long as that
matched one and minus one all of these
have two units of energy because they
have two oscillators of the first
frequency now is there anything else
with the same
energy A2 so let's write down over here
A2 plus o this is
a2+ A- 2 + O
how about
B+ all of these states have um two units
of energy but do they satisfy the level
matching no they either have two units
of Right Moving energy or two units of
left moving energy so these are
illegitimate
States cross them out what's
left what's left is
these okay now I'm going to rewrite them
a little bit different I'm going to
rewrite them in terms of a plus I A plus
I were the operators which make circular
polarization we could write exactly the
same States in a different basis in the
form
a plus I
one one plus
plus times a 1 + i b
+
1 what would you think this
makes anybody got an
idea what did a + I make for the
photon circular polarization which meant
angular momentum plus
one what about
this you've whatever you've done for the
photon you did it
twice spin
two two units of angular momentum going
around the
axis
no no you mean
here
no oh
sorry thank you that's yes you're right
otherwise it wouldn't be level M no no
no no no sorry not right I don't have it
right plus one minus
one this gives you plus one unit of
energy this gives you minus no this
gives you a right moving thing this
gives you a left moving thing right
times left is level matched that's the
right way to think about
it uh what else can you
have same thing except with a minus B *
a minus b i a minus IB how about that
what would that
make if this is like two right-handed
photons adding up to spin two this is
like two left-handed photons adding up
to angular momentum minus two about the
z-axis
all right so first of all we have
angular momentum 2 we have angular
momentum minus 2 there were four
independent states here so we're missing
something four linearly independent
combinations what else can we make we
can make uh let's see we can
make let's just write it A1 + I
B1 I'm not going to write put the pluses
forget the pluses
um a minus1 minus i b Min -
one this is
a plus IB * a minus
IB Left Right Moving left moving how
many units of angular momentum does this
make this is like superposing a right
circularly polarized photon with a left
circularly polarized Photon two
photons zero so this has angular
momentum zero this has angular momentum
let's call it m = 2 this has angular
momentum M = -2 this has M =
0o and the other possibility is to
switch plus and minus one to make this
A1 -
ib1 * a -1 +
ib-1 those
four possibilities are linear
combinations of these
how much angular momentum
here zero
again so we have two states with angular
momentum
zero and two
states or one state with angular
momentum two and one state with angular
momentum minus 2 now let's just remember
what we're doing we have a particle
shooting down the
z-axis whatever it is it seems to come
in a state with angular momentum two and
a state with angular mum minus two and
then maybe some pieces with angular
momentum zero What's missing how could
there's something on the on the face of
it it seems wrong if the spin two there
then there must be a spin two part then
this must be representing somehow a spin
two particle how many states does a spin
two particle
have five and what do they come in m
equals 2
1 0 - one
-2 we we we have a candidate for the
spin zero we have two candidates for the
spin zero but we don't have any
candidate whatever for the spin one and
minus
one no no no no no no no no this is we
said could this be a spin two
particle all right right could it be a
spin two particle forget we're calling
it a graviton let's just call it could
it be a spin two particle a spin two
particle has five states if it was
moving down the axis there you would or
the angular momentum about that axis
would come in a multipet of five
possible
States right but we don't we don't find
the right five possible States we find
four states but not the right not even
uh not even close we're missing the the
m equal 1 and minus one those would be
part of the spin two doubl
it right what do we conclude from that
either the whole thing is a mess and it
doesn't work or what the spin two
particle is
what
massless massless because massless
particles come only in
maximal and minimal angular momentum
States that's a general fact about a
graviton like a photon would have only a
right-handed polarized and a left-handed
polarized the only difference with a
photon is the right-handed polarized
graviton has two units of angular
momentum and the left handed has minus
two units gravitons do not come in
things with angular momentum one or
angular momentum zero so we have here
can the only possible interpretation if
this is to make
sense is that there's a graviton here
but we're left over with two states with
angular momentum zero what could that
be the only thing it could be is two
particles which have angular momentum
zero that's it two particles with
angular momentum zero one of them one
linear combination I think is this plus
this is called the
dilaton it's a scal of particle it's
there in the spectrum of string theory
it has the same mass as the graviton
namely zero mass and the other particle
is called the
axon these are both familiar particles
uh very very familiar particles to um to
phenomenologists and they have one
important common feature they have never
been
discovered
uh that's uh this is a fact about them
in the formal mathematical structure of
the theory they begin as massless
particles the interesting question is
can you get rid of these somehow without
getting rid of this and the answer is
yes these are not necessarily there this
is necessarily there so what we found
then for um for the closed string is
something new we found massless spin two
particles the only thing that we haven't
explained is why this level matching why
do we require this funny rule that the
amount of energy circulating to the
right should be the same as the amount
of energy circulating to the
left maybe we'll go through it it's
um it's not
complicated it is subtle
well left and right doesn't mean in
space it means along the string
right and the condition that the left
moving energy and the Right Moving
energy are the
same well I'll tell you what let's take
a let's take a break for a few minutes
I'll tell you what the condition is I'm
not sure I'll derive it or not but I'll
tell you what the condition which
implies it
is we'll derive it
H okay we've uh We've sort of gotten
into the technical details of the
spectrum of strings and so forth and uh
and the one missing piece was this level
matching I'm going to tell you what the
level matching is now what it means
first of
all and then I will derive it for
you whether you will recognize the steps
in the derivation or not I don't know
we one formulation uses nerus theorem
maybe I won't even have to use nerus
theorem but we'll
see
um the question is is the point Sigma
equals z really a physically special
point or is
or doesn't it matter which point you
call Sigma equals z
there's another way of asking the
question of whether the state of a
string should be
invariant under changing what you call
the origin of the sigma
coordinate now it's not obvious what the
answer is it could be that uh it could
be that there's a special point on the
string that's marked by a little piece
of little bit of ink you know like a uh
uh and uh that uh Point can be special
right
it could also be that there is nothing
special about any point and that the
theory has to be symmetric or
invariant under Shifting the parameter
Sigma that's what it comes down to and
whether the states of a string are
invariant with respect to shifting that
parameter that is a fundamental question
it's clearly a fundamental question I
haven't stated exactly what it means
yet uh but U I'll state it now we could
begin by thinking of the string as a
discrete collection of
points and then in have instead of
having X of
Sigma and Y of Sigma we would have X
of
I let's call it X of I and Y subi what
is xui and Y subi X subi and Y subi are
just the positions of the point I units
down the string I might run from 1 to
n up to
n all right now uh next what is the
Quantum wave function of a of a string
well if we think of the string as just a
collection of Point particles at least
temporarily then the wave function of a
string the quantum State the quantum
State Vector of a
system what would it be a function
of the X's the positions x's and y's let
me leave out the the Y's X1 X2 X3 dot
dot dot up to
xn but why did I start with X1 over here
why didn't I start with X2 over there
and cycle around and say s of X2 dot dot
dot dot dot
xn
X1 no special
reason why not because there's nothing
special about the point that starts out
at the that Sigma equals zero now what
about the quantum wave function of a
string which is completely symmetric
with respect to reordering the X's I
don't want to reorder them in in the
sense of putting X3 between X1 and X2
that's too violent a uh thing to do that
takes a point rips the string open but
just en cycling
them all right
a string which has no preferential point
should have the property that the wave
function when expressed in terms of X1
X2 X3 X xn should equal the wave
function if you substitute it for X1 X2
2 for X2 X3 for X3 X4 and so forth
should also equal s of x3 dot dot dot
dot dot dot dot xn X1
x2 in other words the wave function
should have a certain
symmetry that it should be invariant
with respect to um to Shifting the
label I from I to I + one that's a
possible thing that we might demand of a
string theory it's not only a possible
thing that we might demand we get into
really big trouble if we don't really
big trouble the whole works uh just uh
falls
apart
okay what does that have to do with
level matching nothing obvious but
everything let's leave this up here
okay supposing now I go from the discret
string to the continuous
string what's the corresponding thing
here instead of saying that the Symmetry
is or the uh operation of interest is x
i goes to x i Plus
One modulo n cycling around on N what uh
what's the right thing to say if the
index I is replaced by the continuous
variable
Sigma right right so it says that the
wave
function which is a function
of X of Sigma
it's a function of a function what's a
function of a function called function a
functional so the wave function is a
function of X of
Sigma and if Sigma equals z was not
special that wave function should not
change if we
shift as Michael
said we simply shift the argument we
shift the the uh the sigma variable to
Sigma plus Epsilon now Sigma plus
Epsilon of course means something uh you
at the point 2 pi you want to shift it
it doesn't you know it means a little uh
re a little rotation of the uh of the
sigma
Circle
okay let's see if we can work out this
is actually just some simple of course
we have to change all of the X's we
don't just change the X at one point
Sigma we change the X's at all point
sigmas in other words we have some x's
along here we shift each point to the
neighboring point so this actually is a
um an operation which changes all of the
X's it changes all of the X's by
shifting them to the neighboring points
okay let's see if we can write down this
in another way let me rewrite it by
writing s of X of Sigma minus
s of X of Sigma like this equals
zero It's a Small Change in the wave
function if I make this little change
where every X goes to the X at the
neighboring
position uh
where
well you're saying
S no it's the same
function yeah okay
yeah same
function okay this equals
zero all right let's work it
out what we've done here is taken a
function of a variable it's actually a
functional of a continuous uh set of uh
things but let's just treat it as a
function how do we calculate what's
going on here well
we write that this is the small change
in
s when you
change X at Point
Sigma times the change in
X this is the change in s when you
change x times the change in X how much
does X
Change how much does X changing going
from X at Sigma plus Epsilon to X at
Sigma
partial of X with respect to Sigma time
Epsilon so this is the change in s when
you change X at Sigma times the change
in X
Sigma when you shift Sigma a little bit
and that's just the derivative of x with
respect to
Sigma time
Epsilon now which Sigma am I talking
about am I talking about Sigma at the
origin Sigma at pi Sigma what the what
so what does it mean here what should I
do is this a separate equation for each
Sigma no you should add them all up
you're saying the change in side when
you change something at one point plus
the change in side when you change it at
the next point plus the change in side
when you change it at the next point and
so forth this really should be integral
D
Sigma the sum of all the changes in s
when you shift each x a little bit
should all add up to zero that's what
this
says we can get rid of the Epsilon
now now what is d x by D Sigma what is
sorry what is DCI by DX let's go back to
Quantum Mechanics let's go back to
quantum mechanics
in quantum mechanics we again have p's
and
q's but how is a p related to the
corresponding Q in quantum
mechanics minus I HR
times d by
DQ momenta are the action of a momentum
on a wave function is to differentiate
it with respect to the corresponding
coordinate okay so whenever you see a
wave function having been differentiated
with respect to a coordinate let's
forget
H whenever you see a wave function
having been differentiated with respect
to a coordinate you can rewrite that as
the action of the corresponding momentum
on
S well here we have the wave function
differentiated with the coordinate at
Point
Sigma what should I write that
as
it's p
Sigma what does that mean p Sigma let's
think about what it means P Sigma we
have a
string and it has a bunch of points X of
Sigma and of of course the points have
velocities the velocities of those
points are their
momenta remember we're just doing
basically non-relativistic uh physics we
know in non-relativistic physics
velocity is
momentum so all this is now is that each
point on this string here each little
Mass Point has its own momentum P of
Sigma and what do I find I find out that
the condition that the wave
function be invariant under
reparameterizations of the pH of the
sigma axis in other words just shifting
the sigma axis is the condition that a
certain integral P of Sigma * the XD
Sigma is equal to zero but P of Sigma is
nothing but where is
it is nothing but the
velocity x dot of
Sigma or DxD
to the integral over
Sigma of D XD to time D XD Sigma should
be
zero that's the condition that there's
no special point now this is highly
abstract it's rather remarkable that uh
that such a condition should exist and
it's and it's rather remarkable that
what it says is that there's no
preferred point on the sigma axis but
now look at it and compare it with this
incidentally I wrote energy here these
should be
integrated the left remember what this
was remember these the left moving
energy and the Right Moving
energy the left moving energy and the
Right Moving
energy
okay the sum of the left moving energy
and the Right Moving energy is just the
energy what about the difference of the
left moving energy and the Right Moving
energy what's left over when you take
the difference instead of the sum let's
take the
difference difference of the left moving
energy and the Right Moving energy
what's left
this
okay um and I don't even have no half
here but
do
matter if you were to take the
difference of the left for whatever
reason let's take the difference of the
left moving energy and the Right Moving
energy then the DX by D to squares would
cancel the DX by D Sigma squares would
cancel but the cross terms would add and
you would be left with exactly
this right so the condition that the
wave function not change when you shift
the sigma ax AIS winds up being nothing
but the statement that the left moving
energy and the Right Moving energy
should be the same isn't that
curious that's the condition if you have
a
string or if you have a theory of
strings which says that there are no
Preferred Points or no that the sigma
axis does not have any preferred point
and that the wave function or the state
Vector of the string doesn't change when
you just arbitrarily come and change the
sigma parameterization you shift the
sigma axis then that becomes the
condition that the left moving energy
and the Right Moving energy are equal
that was the level matching condition
left moving energy equals Right Moving
energy so the content
of throwing away all these states which
don't match the energy going around this
way and energy going around that way
that's the content of saying that uh
with talking about a theory of strings
in which the string does not have a
preferred point along its Sigma
direction does not have a special Point
that's called Sigma equals z i find this
a very beautiful fact in many ways and
it throws away a very large portion of
the spectrum that you can make out of
the strings happens that it throws away
just the portion which you can't fit
together into angular momentum
multiplets of uh sensible particles
uh it throws away for example those uh
well okay it throws away big chunks of
the of the
spectrum leaves the
photon Photon why does it leave the
photon because the photons are open
strings and it doesn't care about this
it leaves the
graviton and it leaves the dilaton and
it leaves the Axion as the massless
strings and then whatever else is there
so you can work out for yourself what
would be at the next level the next
level uh and see if you can make some
sense out of them anyway I think uh
that's what I had wanted to do today
it's a
lot but uh you see that there is some
there are things you can understand but
you've got to be guided through them I
think uh somebody asked me an
interesting question well there were two
interesting questions um one of them was
simply a confusion but uh the confusion
was obviously because I had gone quickly
I just wanted remind you again and again
and again what I mean by left moving and
Right Moving I've used the ter or
clockwise and anticlockwise I've
inadvertently used the term in two
different ways I want to distinguish
them one of them had to do with n and
minus in and that had to do with waves
which were moving along the plus Sigma
Axis or the minus Sigma axis that had
nothing whatever to do with orientation
in Space the other way I used it was in
talking about the polarization States of
photons and talking about circular
polarization I said right circular
polarization left circular po that was
really in genuine space x and y space so
we must not confuse those two even
though I use the same terminology for
them the other question that I was asked
we've been going through some of the
technical details of string theory what
is it what the what kind of
constructions go into
it um ask me what
I don't know whether to call it a
philosophical question or
not uh it's not a philosoph it's a good
it's philosophical questions are by
definition bad
questions uh this was not a bad question
it was whether one way or another is
there any either evidence or reason to
believe that in some sense strings are
the most fundamental things could
strings be made of other things is uh I
I think it's a kind of a question of in
the march of
reductionism the is there some sense in
which strings are the most fundamental
things in the world and there's nothing
smaller than them or they're not made of
anything and I gave an answer which was
the ultimate hedge or the ultimate um
waffle the ultimate
waffle and that
was we have learned that that's not a
good question so so let me say a little
bit about it I'll go back to the issue
of monopoles for a moment remember the
monopole why because I want to ask the
question which is more fundamental the
electron or the
monopole is a monopole more fundamental
or is the electron more
fundamental and I want to raise this
issue of uh of
uh all right so let's Suppose there
really are monopoles in quantum electrc
Dynamics it's easy to formulate the
quantum electrodynamics so that there
are monopoles in it and ask which is
more fundamental now let me remind you
the I from what I told you before the
electric
charge times the monopole
charge has to equal 2
pi in order for
what in order for the direct string
which is the
solenoid which is connected to the
monopole to be
invisible this is the condition that if
you have a monopole and it's connected
to a long string it's the only way to
make a monopole
mathematically that charged particles
which uh go around the string don't
detect the phase
shift e * Q is equal to 2
pi that means if the electric charge is
very small now first of all if the
electric charge is very small then we
get to do Quantum electrodynamics in the
way that we've all learned how to do it
Fineman diagrams and so forth Fineman
diagrams are not very effective if the
electric charge is large why
not yeah because each findan diagram
contains a bunch of vertices each
verticy each vertex has an e squ in the
probability uh if e is large then it
means that the Fineman di the values of
the Fineman diag Rams get bigger and
bigger and bigger as the size of the
diagrams get bigger and bigger and they
don't converge you can't add them up
they don't converge to anything so
findan diagrams are explicitly a tool
for studying theories with small charges
they just won't work be useless for
theories with big charges the other hand
here we have a theory which has a small
electric charge let's assume the
electric charge is small but if the
electric charge is small the magnetic
charge is very big
uh if we tried to
Interchange the electric charge and the
Magnetic
charge we might think well electric and
magnetic fields this sort of the same
not the same thing but they're
interchangeable Maxwell's
equations uh the equations for electric
fields and magnetic fields are
completely symetric with respect to each
other there some minus signs but those
are uh you can you can deal with them
electric and magnetic just completely
parallel with respect to each other so
supposing the theory does have magnetic
charges how do we know which of the two
kinds of charge electric or magnetic is
more fundamental so you might say okay
let's go
back and try working with the magnetic
monopoles as the fundamental charges
redo fineman's whole
exercise interchanging electric charges
and magnetic charges you could do it
it's perfectly doable but you would find
out that if you tried doing the findan
diagrams in terms of the magnetic
monopoles because the magnetic charge is
large you they wouldn't converge right
so it's
useful to think of the electric charges
as the fundamental objects now another
thing the magnetic charges being large
that suggests that the mass of a
monopole will be large why because they
have electric and magnet they have field
energy associated with them the field
energy of a magnetic charge will be much
bigger than the field energy of an
electric charge and so they'll be
heavier because they're strongly
interacting that means that a magnetic
charge will be very effective at a
emitting a
photon an electric charge will emit a
photon about 1 out of 137% of the
time the magnetic charge will emit a
photon 137 squared times stronger so
this magnetic charge is going to be
surrounded by an incredibly dense sea of
photons but the photons are going to
interact very strongly with pairs of
magnetic charges make pairs of magnetic
charges and it's going to turn the
magnetic monopole into a very very
complicated thing with all kinds of
internal structure and in fact it's
going to spread it out over a larger
volume it's going to make it
heavier it's going to make it
complex and it's going to make it
useless as a starting point for finding
diagrams does that mean that the
magnetic fi that the magnetic charges
are in any sense less
fundamental well that that I think is a
matter of taste but here's what I can
tell you you could start gradually
changing the parameters of the
theory increase the electric charge it's
just a number in the equations you could
imagine slowly increasing it in fact you
can really imagine slowly increasing the
the magnitude of the electric charge and
at some
point these will become equal e and
Q beyond that
Q will become smaller than e what
happens the magnetic charge becomes more
the magnetic
charges start to play the role that the
electric charges originally did the
electric charges become the complicated
heavy things the magnetic charges become
the simple light
things um the question of whether
something is
composite or
fundamental is should really be asked in
the in the following way you should ask
is it useful to think of it one way or
the other and whether it's useful or not
may depend on the values of the
parameters in the
theory it may depend on the values they
may depend on the
environment there might even be
situations where there are control knobs
that you can turn which winds up turning
the magnetic charges into something more
fundamental in electric charges this
really can happen you can imagine this
happening and so there's no
invariant ultimate answer to the
question which is more fundamental the
magnetic charge or the electric charge
it's a question of which is useful I
remember this this question came up um
in a salv conference once in in Texas oh
it must have been 20 25 years ago I
don't remember and I was giving a
lecture the lecture was on the higs
bosan and the question was is the higs
bosan fundamental or is it
composite and I was describing a theory
in which the higs bosan is composite and
Eugene wigner the famous Eugene wigner
who raises his hand and he said vas
means
composite and I said that means uh you
know things made out of a little pieces
and so forth yeah Bas means composite
and explained it over into again and no
it doesn't mean composite what composite
means is that it can't be broken
up it can't Decay it can't Decay the
thing can't Decay no sorry fundamental
means it can't
Decay and composite means it can Decay
it can break up it can fall apart so I
asked him well Eugene do you think that
that means that the hydrogen atom is
fundamental because the ground state of
the hydrogen atom is fundamental because
it can't Decay no no no no no no
no and we we started to talk about the
proton the proton can't Decay is it
fundamental and the neutron not
fundamental because it can the whole
argument got really crazy nobody was
making any progress in explaining what
and everybody and his brother had some
opinion about what composite and
fundamental means and finally Gerard OU
who was always the most sensible person
at these things got up and simply said a
thing is fundamental when it's useful to
think of as fundamental and everybody
shut up because they knew he was
absolutely
right
uh that is now are strings fundamental
there is one set of parameters in the
theory where strings are made up out of
little things called Deb brains you
change the parameters and you find that
de brains are made up out of the strings
so it's a question
of useful there are ranges of the
parameters of the theory where is useful
to think of the strings as the most
fundamental objects you can shift the
parameters and find ranges of parameters
where the things that are called de
brains which previously have been
thought of as big fat composite objects
similar to the monopoles morph into tiny
things and the strings themselves blow
up into big fat composit
uh this is a lesson that I think physics
has been driving at for some time the
sort of continuous March of
reductionism smaller things made of
smaller things made of smaller things
and some ultimate sense of what the most
fundamental thing is that does not seem
to be the way things are going the way
things are going is that things morph
into each other when you change the
parameters in the theory Theory and what
was fundamental can become composite
what was composite can be fundamental
what the ultimate um lesson to learn
there nobody knows but uh it is it is a
a pattern that's been emerging over the
last you know 20 years both in Quantum
field Theory that's here electrons and
uh and also in string
theory so we'll hopefully get to see
some of that
um we're finished I think with closed
and open strings I think what we're
going to do is jump to a new
subject which is string theory of course
but as seen from a totally different
angle the angle it's called M
Theory okay and I'm going to tell you
what M Theory is and then how M Theory
becomes String Theory what we haven't
talked about yet is why 26 Dimensions
why 10 Dimensions we can talk about that
but we can't talk about everything so I
thought I would tell you what m theor is
and how it relates to string
theory okay I think we're finished with
tonight for more please visit us at
stanford.edu